Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Stereographs 1850-1964 (Bulk 1860-1900) PR 65
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society collection of stereographs
1850-1964
New-York Historical Society
PR 65
82 Linear feet 17,301 items in 88 boxes
This collection, formerly known as the Stereograph File, consists of materials published in the stereographic form, which when seen through a viewer gives the impression of being a three dimensional representation. The bulk of the collection consists of paper stereographs (which range in size from 3 1/8 x 6 3/4 inches to 4 x 7 inches) published between 1860-1900, including albumen and silver gelatin prints. There are also early glass stereographs, tissue stereographs, tintypes, and photomechanically produced views. The views were acquired from a variety of sources over the last 130 years and represent the work of a large variety of photographers and publishers. Most of the collection depicts identifiable geographic locations or subject matter. There are a number of Civil War stereographs; these have been digitized and are available online via New York Heritage. There are also views that were staged in a dramatic fashion to tell a story or convey emotional content.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of material in the Stereograph Collection is from the collection of George T. Bagoe, and was donated by Mrs. Elihu Spicer in 1960-1961. Another series was taken by Alfred C. Loonam in the 1950s and 1960s, and donated by his wife. Others were purchased, or transferred from other institutions. There are over 300 accession dates and numerous sources recorded.
Access Restrictions
For more information on making arrangements to consult the collection, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Historical Note
Over 800 photographers and publishers created the work represented in the Stereograph Collection. Major publishers including E & H.T. Anthony, Keystone, Underwood & Underwood, and Kilburn Brothers make up much of the collection. Views by well-known western photographers Carleton Watkins, William Henry Jackson, J.J. Reilly, and C.R. Savage are included, along with photographers who worked in eastern locales such as John P. Soule, D. Barnum, the Bierstadt Brothers, and George Barker. Many of the photographers worked in established tourist areas, such as Niagara Falls however, dozens of photographers working in their local areas are also included in the file. Portraitists who worked in stereo include Mathew Brady, Pach Brothers, Napoleon Sarony and J. Gurney & Son. Some of the photographers were amateurs, such as F. F. Thompson, who photographed Central Park in the 1860s and was one of the founders of the Amateur Photographic Exchange Club. Another significant amateur was Alfred T. Loonam, whose stereographs of New York in the 1950s and 1960s capture modern skyscrapers, expressways under construction, and the emerging television industry.
Scope and Content Note
Views in the Stereograph Collection depict a wide range of subject matter. Most of the items show known locations, and over one third of the collection depicts New York state. 4,000 of these items depict New York City. Other well-represented geographic locations include California, with 739 items, Massachusetts with 598, Pennsylvania with 798, New Hampshire with 475, Washington, D.C. with 320, New Jersey with 226 and Connecticut with 210. Subject areas with substantial holdings include the Civil War, Indians of North America, and the expeditions in the west led by Fisk, Hayden, Powell and Wheeler. The Civil War stereographs have been digitized and and are available online via New York Heritage.There are also a substantial number of portraits, primarily those of celebrities.
Items in the series that are arranged geographically depict homes, churches and other institutions and organizations, public buildings, offices, schools, restaurants, farms, businesses and industries, and include some interior views. Industries that are well represented include mining, logging, shipping, and the early petroleum industry in Pennsylvania. Because of a personal interest on the part of George T. Bagoe, who collected many of the stereographs in the file, the files contain many views of photographers or their studios or equipment. Sometimes the views depict historically significant sites, such as the Old North Church in Boston, and the armory where John Brown was captured in Harper's Ferry.
Many types of transportation are depicted. Railroads, particularly the Central and Union Pacific, and the Pennsylvania Railroads are well represented. There are images of the Erie and Delaware and Hudson canals, as well as ocean and river shipping. Stagecoaches, carriages, carts and wagons, omnibuses and street-railroads are seen in street views and in the country. Elevated railroads and the subway in New York City are documented, and even modern expressways were photographed in stereo and included in the file.
Community activities such as parades, anniversaries of historic events and holidays such as the Fourth of July are documented, as well as the sports of rowing, croquet, archery, horseback riding and hunting. Other activities for enlightenment and amusement photographed include camp meetings and chatauquas, reading, band concerts, circuses, merry-go-rounds, and picnicking.
Tourist attractions are also well represented, including Niagara Falls, the Grand Canyon and mountains in New Hampshire and Colorado, and hot and mineral springs. Also present are souvenirs of the Centennial Exposition of 1876, and the World's Columbian Exposition, as well as exhibitions in the Crystal Palace in London and various expositions in Paris.
Photographers and publishers also took advantage of spectacular events to produce and market stereographs, including, balloon ascensions, Blondin crossing Niagara Falls on tightrope, the Chicago and Boston fires, the San Francisco earthquake, train wrecks, dam failures, tornado damage and other disasters. Scientific discoveries and technological advances were a focus of public interest in the nineteenth century and are also represented in the stereographs. Feats of engineering such as canals, railroads, aqueducts and bridges are well represented. In addition there are views showing a fascination for scientific advances and discoveries, such as images of the fraudulent Cardiff Giant, and views of the full moon.
There are many kinds of people depicted in the file. The official visits of the Japanese embassy, the Prince of Wales and the Grand Duke of Russia in the 1860s are all documented. Other foreign-born individuals are identified, including Chinese laborers in Massachusetts and California, and Irish-, German-, and Scandinavian Americans. African Americans are depicted in many locales, as are Native Americans. A fascination with people with different life-styles is evident in the images of the Shakers, the Oneida Community and the Mormons. The collection database provides indexing for various classes of people, such as women, and children.
War has offered perennial subject matter for stereographers. Some of the earliest views in the collection show Crimean War sites. Besides the heavily documented United States Civil War, other military actions that were recorded include the Modoc Indian War, the Spanish American War, South African War (Boer War), the Russo-Japanese War, and World War I. Usually the scenes do not show battle action, but are important for the images of soldiers, battlefields, armaments and important persons related to the war.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 3 series: Geographic, Subject, and Comic and Sentimental. Each series is arranged into groups of items, and each group has an Identifier, or unique number. The Identifier can be found within the group's Scope and Contents note.
Geographic Series: The bulk of the collection consists of geographic views. Items are arranged into groups, and each group has an Identifier, or unique number. The Identifier can be found within the group's Scope and Contents note. Wherever possible items are arranged in the smallest geographic group possible, usually a town. Large cities may be covered by many groups of items and the views divided up by location within the city, or by subject. If there are only one or two items for a particular geographic unit, they may be combined with other items and described under the name of the next larger geographic unit, such as the state. In general, the groups go from the general to the specific, with groups covering entire states followed by more specific locations within the state.
Subject Series: This series is arranged by subject or topic. Items are arranged into groups, and each group has an Identifier, or unique number. The Identifier can be found within the group's Scope and Contents note. Many of the items arranged by subject are of unknown location. Other subjects have known locations, but depict substantial and important subjects, such as the Civil War or the Spanish American War. Some of the items form published series, such as the Powell and Wheeler expeditions in the American West. It may be necessary to search the Geographic Series for subjects that are also represented in the Subject Series. For instance, there is a subject group titled Indians of North America, but there are additional views of Native American Indians dispersed throughout the Geographic Series.
Comic and Sentimental Series: This series consists of views that were staged to tell a story or to depict a scene from literature. Items are arranged into groups, and each group has an Identifier, or unique number. The Identifier can be found within the group's Scope and Contents note. The groups are arranged by published series, or general topic.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Civil War stereographs from this collection have been digitized and are available online via New York Heritage.
The Transparency file includes stereoscopic views, including glass and film views. There are some stereoscopic lantern slides, as well as a large number of Stereo Realist format slides. The Cased Photograph File includes stereographic daguerreotypes.
Albumen prints.; Gelatin silver prints.; Portraits.; Photomechanical prints.; California; Colorado River (Colo.-Mex.) -- Discovery and exploration.; Pennsylvania; New York (State); Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.); United States -- Discovery and exploration.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Chinese Americans; Crimean War, 1853-1856; Disasters -- United States; Diplomats -- Japan.; Exhibitions; Great Fire, Chicago, Ill., 1871; Historic sites -- United States.; Indians Of North America; Interiors.; Shipping; World War, 1914-1918.; African Americans.; Associations, institutions, etc. -- United States.; Camp meetings -- United States.; Canals -- United States.; Mines and mineral resources -- United States.; Modoc Indians -- Wars, 1873; Petroleum industry and trade -- United States.; Parades.; Parks; Photographers.; Public buildings.; Schools -- United States.; Shakers; Spanish-American War, 1898; Railroads -- United States.; Tourism -- United States.; Souvenirs.; Photographic prints.; Stereographs.; Pach Brothers (Firm); Sarony, Napoleon, 1821-1896; Soule, John P. (Photographer); Thompson, F. F. (Photographer); Underwood & Underwood; Watkins, Carleton E., 1829-1916; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.) [111]; Barker, George, 1844-1894; Bierstadt Brothers; Brady, Mathew B., approximately 1823-1896; Centennial Exhibition (1876: Philadelphia, Pa.) [111]; E. & H.T. Anthony (Firm); Geological Survey of the Territories (U.S.); J. Gurney & Son; Jackson, William Henry, 1843-1942; Keystone View Company; Kilburn Brothers; Loonam, Alfred T. (Photographer)
- Geographic, 1850-1964
  Scope and Contents
  Geographic Series: The bulk of the collection consists of geographic views. Items are arranged into groups, and each group has an Identifier, or unique number. The Identifier can be found within the group's Scope and Contents note. Wherever possible items are arranged in the smallest geographic group possible, usually a town. Large cities may be covered by many groups of items and the views divided up by location within the city, or by subject. If there are only one or two items for a particular geographic unit, they may be combined with other items and described under the name of the next larger geographic unit, such as the state. In general, the groups go from the general to the specific, with groups covering entire states followed by more specific locations within the state.
  - Alabama, 1900 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Identifier: PR-065-0001
    Cotton being loaded on a steamer, Mobile, Alabama
  - Alaska, 1866 - [1910] (Box 1)
    Identifier: PR-065-0002
    General views of Bella Bella, Fort Wrangle, Sitka and Kass (an Indian village with totem poles); Street view in Wrangel; railroad surveyors in camp; interior of a home; cabin in Cape Nome; men canoeing through canyon; the steamer Spokane, with mountains rising in the background.
    12 items
  - Alaska--Gold rush, 1898 - 1902 (Box 1)
    Identifier: PR-065-0003
    Steamboats in Seattle, on the Klondyke; street views; people on the trail to the gold fields; after a snow slide on Dyea trail searching for the dead; cabins, tents; miners in camp and working (including women); dogteams, packtrains; waiting for mail at Dawson; Sheep Camp.
    20 items
  - Alaska--Gold rush--Chilkoot Pass, 1898 (Box 1)
    Identifier: PR-065-0004
    Miners coming up the trail to and passing over the Chilcoot pass, carrying all kinds of gear, including sleds and canoes; gear ready to be hauled over; a view of an aerial tram transporting goods; shacks and tents at the base of the pass.
  - Arizona, [1870 - 1879] (Box 1)
    Identifier: PR-065-0005
    Military: Camp Bowie (incl. military parade), Camp Grant, soldiers in the desert among cactus; copper mining; railroad bridge, Canyon Diablo; steamboat, Colorado R. landing; cattle ranch; Prescott: general views, which can make up a panorama if viewed in sequence, courthouse; church, incl. interior, Tuscon; hotel, landing, bridge at Yuma.
    29 items
  - Arizona--Grand Canyon, 1903 - 1909 (Box 1)
    Identifier: PR-065-0006
    Views of the Grand Canyon, the Colorado River and tourists visiting. Some tourists shown at the edge of precipice, some on horseback on trails, and some on the banks of the Colorado River, including a view of the painter Thomas Moran.
    28 items
  - Arizona--Indians of North America, 1870-1903 (Box 1)
    Identifier: PR-065-0007
    Indians in Arizona including Navajos in front of a hogan, Meeshomoneah, and pueblo, Wolpi, a Hopi Pueblo, "ration day" at San Carlos Pueblo, and ruins at Casa Grande.
    7 items
  - Arkansas, [1870 - 1879] (Box 1)
    Identifier: PR-065-0008
    Men on rough-hewn benches, soaking their feet in the foot bath, or "corn hole"; man on horseback, with caption "Arkansas traveler"
    2 items
  - California, 1865 - 1900 (Box 2)
    Identifier: PR-065-0009
    House and garden of J. C. Ralston in Belmont, including one interior view; general view of and store at Camp Bidwell, Surprise Valley; large oak at Carlin; Freight teams on the road outside of and the streets of Cisco; Faralllon Island, and portrait of bird or egg hunters; lumber industry, Mendocino City, including a lumber flume, views on the Noyo River, ships in Little River Harbor, log rafts and log jams and the Albion Mill; Indian baskets on the bank of Mono Lake; general view of Monterey, and Midway Point from Cypress Drive; Nordhoff Hotel in the Ojai Valley; the Stanford residence in Palo Alto; Marengo Ave. and oranges, Pasadena; century plant in bloom, man irrigating orange grove, Riverside; unidentified mission church; street scenes in San Bernardino, San Buenaventura, Santa Cruz; general views of San Diego; orange groves and Sierra Madre Villa, San Gabriel; courthouse in San Jose; general view of San Mateo, including church; men on wharf, Santa Ana; hotel, rail wharf and bath house, Santa Monica; men drinking at Tuolumne soda Springs; Mount Shasta; a log or lumber flume in San Lorenzo; steam thresher on wheat farm. Sacramento valley; tourists at White Sulphur Springs, Napa; views of Southern Pacific trains and works at Wilmington; Digger Indians outside dwelling; unidentified home; views of camping in California, including M.M. Hazeltine and F. J. Woodard camping out on Big River.
    62 items
  - California--Big Trees, 1870 - 1901 (Box 2)
    Identifier: PR-065-0010
    Tourists visiting Sequoia groves in Calaveras, Mariposa and Tuolumne Counties; views of trees, including the Wawona Tunnel tree with coaches passing through it, the interior of a house built on a tree stump, images of trees standing a fallen, one with a tent pitched on it. Also includes cabins and a hotel.
    32 items
  - California--Central Pacific Railroad & Sierras, 1866 - [1888] (Box 2)
    Identifier: PR-065-0011
    Views along the track of the Central Pacific Railroad and in the surrounding Sierra Mountains, including trains, one with snow plow on the front, other with excursionists posing, snow sheds, stations and hotels, log cabins, tunnels, trestle and covered bridges, camps, including Chinese workers' and a tent camp at the end of the track, workers (including Chinese workers) hauling freight, blasting, building banks, ferry steamers and trains at the terminus, an Indian viewing railroad from top of Palisades, a group of Indians at Humboldt station, dugout at Donner Lake, stumps from trees that the Donner party cut; Lake Anna; winter scene in Colfax; basaltic rocks in Truckee Canyon; Truckee City, Lake Tenaya, Palisade City. Includes images of photographers and cameras (Hart)
    135 items
  - California--Geysers, [1870] - [1889] (Box 2)
    Identifier: PR-065-0012
    Tourists visiting the geysers in Sonoma county: riding in coaches, at hotels, cooking eggs in the "Witches Cauldron," posing near a steam bath and a Native American Indian sweat bath.
    23 items
  - California--Gold mining, 1866 - [1880] (Box 3)
    Identifier: PR-065-0013
    Gold mining in California, including placer mining, and hydraulic mining: dumps, sluices, flumes, hoist wheels and rockers. Miners guiding pipes directing water against hillsides, and panning for gold, including one Chinese miner. General views of mining camps. mines, and environmental degradation. Includes views in the Sierras, and in the Russian River country.
    26 items
  - California--Los Angeles, [1870] - [1905] (Box 3)
    Identifier: PR-065-0014
    Views of Los Angeles and vicinity: views of downtown showing businesses including a photographer's studio; the railroad depot; La Plaza; scene of the Chinese riot (with a stage coach in foreground); general views; a view of the "Old Round House"; women in a flower-covered coach in a parade; views of plants including a date tree, orange trees, roses, figs, persimmon tree; a garden with cactus; grapes laid out to dry for raisins; workers packing oranges; general view of Sonora.
  - California--Modoc War, 1873 (Box 3)
    Identifier: PR-065-0015
    Modoc War showing the camp at Tule Lake showing tents, one view with soldiers arrayed in front and including site where General Canby was shot by Captain Jack, and Tule Lake beyond; views of the lava beds from the signal station, and views in the lava beds, including a cave, pickets on the lookout, soldiers in the Modoc stronghold after its capture, and Modoc Indians posing; Donald McKy and other Warm Springs Indian scouts, One Eyed Dixie, Toby and other Modoc squaws; wounded being brought back on litter mounted on a mule; group portrait of General Davie Hardie, General Gillem and officers of the Modoc campaign; journalist in the field.
    19 items
  - California--Sacramento, [1860] - [1880] (Box 3)
    Identifier: PR-065-0016
    Views in Sacramento: river, levee and piers, steamboats, the railroad, including a bridge across the Sacramento River, the depot, including a view of a sheep herder with a sheep, and Pullman Palace cars; general and street views including the St. George's Hotel, the State House, Odd Fellows building, a bank; the court house; railroad hospital for employees of Central Pacific Railroad; residences of Albert Gallatin and Judge N. Greene Curtis (Formerly owned by T. J. Milliken), Dr. Light's office with Light and others at gate; churches; the race track with harness racers on the track; view from the capital showing several large [circus?] tents; a Chinese-American business.
    34 items
  - California--San Francisco, [1870] - [1889] (Box 3)
    Identifier: PR-065-0017
    General and street views of San Francisco: churches, homes, businesses, including Baldwin's Hotel, and the Bank of California, Mark Hopkins residence; portrait of the Chinese Merchant and wife.
    9 items
  - California--San Francisco, [1860] - 1904 (Box 4)
    Identifier: PR-065-0018
    General and street views of San Francisco: panoramas; churches, homes, businesses: hotels, including interiors, Cliff House, Thomas Houseworth and Company Photography studios, the Bank of California, Merchant's Exchange building; Pacific Insurance Co. building; Post Office and Customs House; Mercantile Library; Mark Hopkins residence; Gov. Frederick F. Low's residence; Mansion house and Mission Dolores; steamers at piers; Alcatraz from Bay shore and Fort Point road; Woodward's Gardens including bears in the bear pit and a balloon ascension; men on ship or yacht, San Francisco Bay, Golden Gate in background; Chinese astrologer outside Joss House; entrance to the Presidio; Fort Point; damage from the Oct 21, 1861 earthquake.
    80 items
  - California--San Francisco--by Watkins, 1862 - 1889 (Box 4)
    Identifier: PR-065-0019
    General and street views of San Francisco, including panoramas and a general view made July 4, 1862; Golden Gate from Nob Hill; Bank of California; Masonic Temple; hotels including the court of the Palace Hotel; sea lions at Woodward's Gardens; trolleys and cable cars; churches; residences of Gov. Stanford, Mark Hopkins, Charles Crocker; Bartlett Alley in the Chinese quarter; portrait of two Chinese women in Chinese restaurant; Cliff house.
    39 items
  - California--San Francisco--Earthquake and Fire, 1906 (Box 4)
    Identifier: PR-065-0020
    Views of the aftermath of the San Francisco earthquake and fire, 1906; includes street views, views of gutted buildings and rubble; people photographing and painting the destruction; bread lines at Jefferson square, tent refugee camps at Golden Gate and other parks, huts made of building materials; people, including a Chinese American man cooking on small stoves at the curb; national guard personnel on patrol; people viewing destruction from carriages and hunting for souvenirs in the rubble; barbering at curbside; people at the ferry landing in Oakland and a relief boat being loaded with supplies; people walking out of the city carrying their bags. Includes one view of firemen fighting the blaze, large plume of smoke in the background.
    69 items
  - California--Santa Barbara, 1870 - 1902 (Box 4)
    Identifier: PR-065-0021
    Santa Barbara: general and street views, including Odd Fellows Hall, the Mission, and homes and businesses; tourists at the hot springs, and cottages and hotels there; people on the grounds in front of Santa Barbara College; Sterns wharf from a hill above; the Mission, including gardens, interiors views, and the reservoirs; Arlington Hotel people wading and on horseback on the beach.
    25 items
  - California--Stockton, 1865 - 1885 (Box 4)
    Identifier: PR-065-0022
    Street scenes in Stockton, including one showing decorations for July 4, 1876. Views include the Odd Fellows building, a hotel, banks and other businesses, and wagons.
    5 items